so we begin executing this instruction
it's a subtraction of 36 minus 3 that's
a result is gonna be 33 and it takes
only one cycle to do adds and subtracts
so this result will be broadcast in
cycle 26 so now the next thing that will
happen is either this or this will be
broadcast cycle 26 is the next cycle so
let's see what happens then in cycle 26
the subtract broadcast the value of 33
under the name of Rob 5 so we mark it as
done
33 gets put here and 30 T under the name
Rob 5 gets broadcast and this
instruction here is waiting for that
value so we get 33 here are no longer
waiting for it
oh yes and because this instruction has
been dispatched early in cycle 24 in
cycle 25 and afterwards this reservation
station has really been freeing so this
instruction although it got now 33 still
is not ready to dispatch because it's
still waiting for Rob 1 so it cannot go
okay so in cycle 27 nothing happens 28
nothing happens in fact the first time
when something does happen from now is
gonna be cycle 42 when the result of Rob
1 is broadcast so let's just kind of
fast-forward there so on let's say we
are now in cycle 42 this divide finally
broadcasts the value of 9 under the name
Rob 1 what happens is when that happens
is we put the 9 here we mark it as done
and then 9 with Rob 1 tag is broadcast
on the bus and all the instructions that
are waiting for that is gonna are gonna
capture that value the only thing that
really needs anything is this and it
captures the value of 9 and it's no
longer waiting for anything so in cycle
43 finally this Rob 6 instruction is
gonna begin execution so with that let's
move to cycle 43 in cycle 43 we begin
execution of this instruction it's an ad
of 33 and 9 so we end up with a 42 value
here this reservation station is now
free this is an ad so it's gonna finish
in cycle 44 there is another thing that
happens in cycle 43 which is OH
this time we have been waiting to commit
this instruction because none of the
other ones can commit until it commits
finally we have been in cycle 42 to
write the results so in cycle 43 we can
actually commit this instruction it's
been marked as done so pretty much the
commit logic is kind of staring at this
entry and waiting to see a cycle where
this entry has a checkmark next to it so
what happens is finally we commit this
in cycle 43 now that this instruction
commits in 43 what's going to happen is
several things first the Rob entry for
this instruction will be freed but
before we freed the Rob entry we need to
update the register file so what's going
to happen is we take this nine and we're
going to write it to register r2 so
register r2 is now going to be written
as nine next we're gonna look at the rat
entry for r2 and see whether it's
pointing to our Rob entry yes it is so
from now on Rob one will be free after
this cycle what we have to do is make
this our two entry point back to the
register file you know so the value of
nine that since recently has been
basically pointing to you know like r2
is here now it's no longer gonna be here
so we need to make it point to r2 is
here I just kind of deleted this but
this really means you can find it in the
register file so now really we are ready
to delete this stuff here and now
finally the divide has fully committed
okay so now if we had an exception or
something basically the divide looks
like it's done all of the other
instructions really are done except for
the last one but they're not considered
done as far as the program order is
concerned basically the commit didn't
get there yet
so now let's move to cycle 44 and see
what happens